Finding Aid for Grand Rapids Urban League Records 1941-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Grand Rapids Urban League records 1941-1986
Grand Rapids Urban League.
Affiliate of the National Urban League. Records include historical information file, administrative files, topical files, and photographs.
851335 Bj 2
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 4177 ) was first deposited with the library in 1964. Additional deposits were made in 1981 and 1995.
The collection is open for research.
The Brough Community Association of Grand Rapids, Michigan was formally incorporated on June 4, 1943. The early aim of the organization was to provide recreational and self-development opportunities for the Grand Rapids Black community. In 1947, the board of directors, anxious to improve and enlarge the programs of the organization, decided to affiliate with the National Urban League. The name of the organization was now changed to the Grand Rapids Urban League and Brough Community Association.
Paul Phillips was named executive secretary of the Association in 1947. Under his leadership, the organization implemented a full Urban League program, and initiated departments in industrial relations, community services, and group work. It also sponsored a women's guild which assisted and made improvements in community race relations.
The League took great pride in opening new employment opportunities for the city's Blacks, as bus drivers, nurses, librarians, and taxi cab drivers. It also set up a scholarship fund to aid students who wanted to attend college. With the passage of years, the Urban League phased out its recreation program, and concentrated instead upon matters of employment, community relations, and housing.
In 1967, the organization amended its articles of incorporation shortening its name to the Grand Rapids Urban League.
The records of the Grand Rapids Urban League document its activities as a civil rights and social service organization serving the African-American community in Grand Rapids. The records have been arranged into four series: Historical/Background Material, Administration Records, Topical Files, and Photographs. The series date from the organization's founding in 1943 up to the mid-1980s. There are numerous gaps in the files with the bulk of the records dating before 1970.
Subjects:
African Americans.; African Americans--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Civil rights--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Brough Community Association of Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids Urban League.; National Urban League.; Social service--Michigan--Grand Rapids--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans--Health and welfare.; African Americans--Organizations.; African Americans--Social life and customs.; Charitable organizations.; Children playing.; Community service.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Brough Community Association of Grand Rapids.; Phillips, Paul.; Photographs.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Historical/background materials
  The Historical Files series consists of a single folder of clippings and miscellaneous material on the history of the Grand rapids Urban League.
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 1)
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series includes the organization's articles of incorporation, minutes of the board of directors and various committees, correspondence files, and reports.
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Annual reports
    - 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1963 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors minutes
    (files and record books containing minutes, reports, memoranda, background information, agenda, etc.)
    - 1941-1946 (Box 1)
      (include minutes of Executive Committee for 1946)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1951 (Box 1)
    - May-December 1951 (Box 1)
    - January-May 1952 (Box 1)
    - June-December 1952 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1953 (Box 1)
    - May-December 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1972-February 1976 (Box 1)
    - October 1976-1979, 1 volumes (Box 1)
      (include executive committee minutes)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 1)
      (1 binder put into expandable folder)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Budgets
    - 1946-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Finance Committee minutes
    - November 1944-September 1950 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1943-1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - 1956 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - Quarterly Reports
    - 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series, alphabetically arranged, includes material on the Urban League's annual meetings, files on various special committees and projects, and reports and studies.
  - Agency Self-evaluation 1954-1956, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Annual Meeting
    - 1946 (Box 3)
    - 1947 (Box 3)
    - 1948 (Box 3)
    - 1949 (Box 3)
    - 1950 (Box 3)
    - 1951 (Box 3)
    - 1952 (Box 3)
    - 1953 (Box 3)
    - 1954 (Box 3)
    - 1955 (Box 3)
  - Board Members Conference 1957 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors
    - Attendance 1956-1976 (Box 3)
    - Business matters 1943-1959 (Box 3)
  - Certificate of Recognition 1950 (Box 3)
  - City Charter Commission 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Clippings
    - Paul Phillips obituary (Box 3)
    - John W. Hall/Walter Brame (Box 3)
  - Committee lists 1943-1959 (Box 3)
  - Community Employment Conference 1957 (Box 3)
  - Election of board members
    - 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Finance and Personnel reports 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Finance Committee minutes 1943-1959 (Box 3)
  - Grand Rapids Youth Commonwealth, Inc. 1948-1951 (Box 3)
  - Grand Rapids Urban League Guild
    - Bylaws 1980-1984 (Box 3)
    - Board-Guild relationship 1982-1985 (Box 3)
    - Guild Bluebook 1985 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Panel of Americans 1985 (Box 3)
  - Group Work and Recreation Committee 1947-1950 (Box 3)
  - Housing study 1952 (Box 3)
  - Industrial Relations Committee 1952-1958 (Box 3)
  - Industrial Relations Workshop 1951, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters of acknowledgment 1944-1949 (Box 3)
  - Long Range Planning Committee, Five Year Plan 1988-1993 (Box 3)
  - Membership award meeting 1954 (Box 3)
  - Membership lists 1943-1972 (Box 4)
  - Membership meeting 1957 (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - National Recreation Association 1944-1949 (Box 4)
  - Open Occupancy Housing Study 1953 (Box 4)
  - Police-Community Relations Institute 1955, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Police-Community Relations Institute 1957-1959 (Box 4)
  - Printed Material
    - Flint Urban League (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids Inter-Tribal Council (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids Urban League (Box 4)
  - Public School Study 1964 (Box 4)
  - Six Cities tour (Germany) 1953, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Special music project 1944-1947 (Box 4)
  - Studies
    - "Four Studies of Grand Rapids Public Schools," April 1964 (Box 4)
    - "Housing of Nonwhites in Grand Rapids, Mich.," May 1964 (Box 4)
    - "The Negro Population of Grand Rapids, Mich.: 1940," April 1940 (Box 4)
    - "A Review of the Progress and Activities of the Brough Community Association," September 10-24, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Whittemore Appreciation Dinner 1953 (Box 4)
  - Women's Guild
    - 1947-1949 (Box 4)
    - 1950 (Box 4)
    - 1951 (Box 4)
    - 1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953 (Box 4)
    - 1954 (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
    - 1956 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1963 (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs Series includes prints of activities of the Grand Rapids Urban League, especially its activities with children (ca. 1950), later activities of the League, and portraits of its secretary, Paul Phillips.
  - Brough Community Association
    - Adults 1950-1951, undated (Box 4)
    - Children circa 1950 (Box 4)
  - Annual Meetings 1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Awards and Presentations 1950 (Box 4)
  - Black employees in Grand Rapids 1947-1965 (Box 4)
    (scattered)
  - Office facilities circa 1950 (Box 4)
  - Paul Phillips
    - Portraits 1956, 1962 (Box 4)
    - City Charter Commission 1951 (Box 4)
    - With Others 1949-1969 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Planning Groups and Committees 1951, undated (Box 4)
  - Women's Guild circa 1960 (Box 4)
  - Individuals 1950, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1954-1961, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (scattered dates)